<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="anc.00243">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main" corresp="lg1860">Leaves of Grass</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">[Review of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1860–61)]</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            
          <author>
                <choice>
                   <orig>unsigned</orig>
                   <reg>unknown</reg>
                </choice>
             </author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               
               
               
               
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>The United States Department of Education</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>anc.00243</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain.</p><p>The text encoding and annotations were created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and are licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author key="unknown">
                     <choice><orig>unsigned</orig>
                        <reg>unknown</reg></choice>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a">Leaves of Grass</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">The Saturday Press</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="1860-09-15">15 September 1860</date>
                     
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
          <p>The electronic text for this file was prepared by <title level="m">Whitman Archive</title> staff, who transcribed the text from a representation of the original (e.g., digital scan or other electronic reproduction, microfilm copy).</p>
       </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-01-19" who="#el">updated author encoding in TEI header</change>
                   <change when="2015-10-19" who="#el">updated rights language and added encoding description in TEI header</change>
         <change who="#no" when="2015-02-26">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-10-03">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">added note to revisionDesc</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">moved bracketed descriptive title to sub title</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">changed author's name in sourceDesc to last name, first</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2007-09-21">copied and encoded from original</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="ancillary">
      <body>

<note type="newspaper-editorial">[From the National Quarterly Review, for September.]</note>
         
         <head type="main-authorial">LEAVES OF GRASS. <!-- [Review of Leaves of Grass (1860&#8211;1861)] --> </head>

         <p>If it be an essential attribute of poetry to afford pleasure and delight to the mind, in proportion as the latter is refined by culture, the performances, entitled 'Leaves of Grass,' have little claim, considered as a poem, to that title; for in no work of the same size have we ever read so much that is disgusting and repulsive. The author seems to exult in being as indecent, obscene, and profane as possible. This is the more to be regretted, because, in the midst of a great deal of the silliest twaddle, and the most unmeaning bombast, we find thoughts of rare beauty and striking force, wonderful felicity of expression, and imagery at once the boldest and most pleasing. Nor are the passages of the latter kind by any means few; although, undoubtedly, the predominating qualities throughout the book are coarseness and vulgarity; so that we often meet with whole stanzas which are too filthy to be quoted. There is a modesty in nature herself, which those who understand her will not overstep; but Walt Whitman (for this we understand is the name of the would-be Homer) goes beyond nature, or rather, in most cases he fails to reach her. Decency requires that we sometimes draw a veil over what is natural; but though such is hidden by common consent, it is not absurd or revolting like many of the images and precepts of Mr. Walt Whitman. We have, now, neither time nor space to illustrate our remarks by suitable extracts. We will, however, give two or three, which we think will sufficiently justify our views, if they do not give a correct idea of the true character of 'Leaves of Grass.' Such egotism and bravado as the following, are to be found at almost every page:</p>


         <!-- From the poem "Walt Whitman" (later: "Song of Myself"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00048" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"I believe in the flesh, and the appetites,</l>
                        <l>Seeing, hearing, feeling, are miracles, and each part <lb/>and tag of me is a miracle.</l>
                     </lg>

                     <lg type="linegroup"> 
                        <l>Divine am I, inside and out, and I make holy <choice><orig>what-<lb/>ever</orig><reg>whatever</reg></choice> I touch, or am touched from,</l>
                        <l>The scent of these arm-pits, aroma finer than prayer,</l>
                        <l>This head more than churches, bibles, and all the creeds.</l>
                        <l>If I worship any particular thing, it shall be some of <lb/>the spread of my own body."—p. 55.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>Be it observed, that this is chaste and decent compared to what follows, but which we take care to omit. Nor is he, generally, much more pleasing or poetical in his scenic descriptions. Thus in describing a sea-fight, he sings (?):</p>

         <!-- From the poem "Walt Whitman" (later: "Song of Myself"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 -->

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00048" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"We had received some eighteen pound shots under the water,</l>
                        <l>On our lower gun-deck two large pieces burst at <lb/>the first fire, killing all around, and blowing up <choice><orig>over-<lb/>head</orig><reg>overhead</reg></choice>."—p. 76.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>As a specimen of his patriotism, we give one stanza:</p>

         <!-- From the poem "Calamus", Leaves of Grass 1860-61 -->

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00066" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"To you of New England,</l>
                        <l>To the man of the sea-side State, and of Pennsylvania,</l>
                        <l>To the Canadian of the North—to the Southerner I <lb/>love,</l>
                        <l>These with perfect trust, to depict you as myself— <lb/>the germs are in all men;</l>
                        <l>I believe the main purport of these States is to be found <lb/>a superb friendship, exalté, previously unknown,</l>
                        <l>Because I perceive it waits, and has been always waiting in all <lb/>men."—p. 374.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>Leaving poetry out of the question, it would be difficult to find duller prose than this. Yet, as we have said, Walt Whitman can be occasionally musical, tender, and pathetic. As an instance, we quote a part of a death-bed scene, which is as beautifully drawn as it is truthful and touching: </p>

         <!-- From the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass; this poem was later modified and became "To Think of Time" -->

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00266" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"When the dull nights are over, and the dull days also,</l>
                        <l>When the soreness of lying so much in bed is over,</l>
                        <l>When the physician; after long putting off, gives the silent and <lb/>terrible look for an answer,</l>
                        <l>When the children come hurried and weeping, and the brothers <lb/>and sister have been sent for,</l>
                        <l>When medicine stand unused on the shelf, and the camphor smell <lb/>has pervaded the rooms,</l>
                        <l>When the faithful hand of the living does not desert the hand of <lb/>the dying,</l>
                        <l>When the twitching lips press lightly on the forehead of the dying,</l>
                        <l>When the breath ceases and the pulse of the heart ceases,</l>
                        <l>Then the corpse-limbs stretch on the bed, and the living look upon <lb/>them,</l>
                        <l>They are palpable as the living are palpable.</l>
                        <l>The living look upon the corpse with their eyesight,</l>
                        <l>But without eyesight lingers a different living and looks curiously <lb/>on the corpse."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>Nor is this, by any means, the best we could cull from the pages of 'Leaves of Grass.' We have read and reread in it many passages much more exquisite; but nevertheless, we cannot regard Walt Whitman as a true poet. That he has genius there can be no doubt, though it is certainly not of a high order. In wading through his uncouth rhapsodies, we are reminded of the pompous, but generally empty speeches which Homer puts into the mouth of Paris, especially of that line in which he makes Helen inform us that the braggart libertine was but ill supplied with sense—</p>

         <q>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <l>Τούτῳ δ' οὒτ' ᾶρ νῦν ϕρένεϛ ἔμεδοι, οὒτ' ἄρ' ὁπίδδω<lb/>ἔδδονται.<ref target="n1" n="1" xml:id="r1"/>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>The publishers have done their part well. A better printed book, coming even from Boston, we have not seen in a good while. We have never seen Walt Whitman to our knowledge; nor do we know anything of him further than we learn from his book, but we think there is reason to fear that he will be too much read by a class of persons not capable of picking the diamonds out of the putrescent filth in which they are imbedded.</p>

      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="notes">

            <p>
               <note type="editorial" target="r1" xml:id="n1" n="1">The <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> 6.352–353: "His mind is not firmly grounded, nor will it ever be; he will reap the fruits of this."</note>
            </p>

         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
