<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="anc.00050">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main" corresp="lg1860">[Review of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1860–61)]</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>
               <choice>
                  <orig>unsigned</orig>
                  <reg>Wathen Mark Wilks Call</reg>
               </choice>
            </author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
               
               
               
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ts">Todd Stabley</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>The United States Department of Education</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>anc.00050</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and is licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of this material should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author key="Call, Wathen Mark Wilks">
                     <choice>
                        <orig>unsigned</orig>
                        <reg>Wathen Mark Wilks Call</reg>
                     </choice>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a">Contemporary Literature</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">The Westminster Review</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="1860-10-01">1 October 1860</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">74</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="issue">n.s. 18</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="pages">590</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
          <p>The original electronic text for this file was prepared for Walt Whitman, <title level="m">The Contemporary Reviews</title>, ed. Kenneth M. Price (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996), and the transcription was completed by consulting a representation of the original (e.g., photocopy, microfilm copy). Following publication of that volume, Price received an updated transcription file from Cambridge University Press, and the <title level="m">Whitman Archive</title> has used the final file from the publisher as the basis for the electronic text presented here.</p>
          </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2016-01-19" who="#el">updated author encoding in TEI header</change>
         <change when="2016-01-19" who="#el">updated author encoding in TEI header</change>
                   <change when="2015-10-19" who="#el">updated rights language and added encoding description in TEI header</change>
         <change who="#no" when="2015-02-26">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#br" when="2012-02-23">changed author name "Anonymous" to "Call, Wathen Mark Wilks" (found in Wellesley Index to Victorian Periodicals)</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-10-03">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">added note to revisionDesc</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">changed author's name in sourceDesc to last name, first</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2007-07-18">"purified" xml; copy-edited transcription and made changes as
necessary</change>
         <change who="#ts" when="2005-11-29">Encoded, validated</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         

         <p>[ . . .]</p>

         <p>If Mr. Walt Whitman's "Leaves of Grass<ref target="n1" xml:id="r1">∗</ref>" had been printed on paper as dirty as his favourite topics,—if the book itself had presented the general aspect of that literature which usually falls under no other criticism than that of the police office, we should have passed it by without notice, as addressing only such a public as we have no concern with; but when a volume containing more obscenity and profanity than is perhaps elsewhere to be found within the same compass, presents itself in all the glories of hot-pressed paper, costly binding, and stereotype printing, and we believe as a fourth edition, it is manifest that it not only addresses, but has found a public of a much wider class, and it becomes a question how such a book can have acquired a vogue and popularity that could induce an American publisher to spend so much upon its outward setting-forth.</p> 

         <p>Perhaps loose thinking and tall talk are nowhere so efficacious in attracting notice as in the United States, and Mr. Whitman, by pretentiously assuming to be the exponent of Hegelian morality, by offering himself as the high-priest of that religion, whose sole dogma is comprised in the proposition <hi rend="italic">Homo sibi deus</hi> [man is god to himself], attracts and perplexes readers, whose natural good sense would otherwise soon cast aside his frightful fustian. That he has any direct acquaintance with those forms of German speculation on which he falls back for the justification of the language he makes use of, we think may be confidently denied, not only from the manner in which he conceives its problems, but from the absence of any German catch words with which he would otherwise have infallibly adorned his motley, for even an ignorance of its grammar does not daunt him when the French language offers a term to his taste. Mr. Emerson has much to answer for, and will in reputation dearly pay for the fervid encomium with which he introduced the Author to the American public. That to the public defence of polygamy and slavery, should now be added that of the emancipation of the flesh, is an indication of a moral disorganization in the States, which is of every evil promise. That a drunken Helot should display himself without shame in the market place, speaks sad reproach to the public that does not scourge him back to his cellar.</p> 

         <p>In form these poems, if poems they can be called, are composed in irregular rhythmical lines, after the manner of Tupper,<ref target="n3" xml:id="r3" n="2"/> and in fact they may be described by the following equation,—as Tupper is to English Humdrum, so is Walt Whitman to the American Rowdy. They have been praised as containing many poetical passages; in this opinion we cannot concur. That sometimes a poetical expression occurs among a dreary waste of rhetorical verbiage may be allowed, but this might have been expected—a naked savage has often a wild grace of movement that a civilized man can hardly possess, but certainly not display.</p> 

         <p>These "Leaves of Grass" are the symptoms of a moral fermentation in America, which no doubt will result in a broader and clearer life—but the progress is painful and the yeast nauseous.</p> 

         <p>[ . . .]</p>

         <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>

         
            
            <ab><hi rend="superscript">∗</hi>
               
                   "Leaves of Grass." 
                   
                      Boston:  
                      Thayer and Eldridge,  
                      year 85 of the States. 1860—61.  
                      London:  
                      Trübner and Co.  
                   
               
            </ab>
          

      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="notes">
            <p>
               <note type="editorial" xml:id="n2" target="r2" n="1">
This review is excerpted from an essay entitled <hi rend="italic">Belles Lettres</hi> that includes reviews on <hi rend="italic">Ethica; or Characteristics of Men, Manners, and Books</hi>, by Arthur Lloyd Windsor; <hi rend="italic">A Sketch of the History of Flemish Literature and Its Celebrated Authors from the 12th Century Down to the Present Time</hi>, by Octave Delepierre; <hi rend="italic">Modern Poets and Poetry of Spain</hi>, by James Kennedy; <hi rend="italic">Scarsdale; or, Lancashire and Yorkshire Borders Thirty Years Ago; Elkerton Rectory, being Part Second of Twenty Years in the Church</hi>, by Rev. James Pycroft; <hi rend="italic">Herbert Chauncy; a Man More Sinned Against Than Sinning</hi>, by A. H. Elton; <hi rend="italic">The Queen's Pardon</hi>, by Mary Eyre; <hi rend="italic">Castle Richmond; a novel</hi>, by Anthony Trollope; <hi rend="italic">Vier Neue Novellen</hi>, by Von Paul Heyse; <hi rend="italic">Maria Regina, eine Erzählung aus der Gegenwart</hi>, by Von Ida Gräfin Hahn-Hahn; <hi rend="italic">Briefe an eine Freundin aus den Jahren 1844 bis 1853</hi>, by Von Varnhagen von Ense; <hi rend="italic">Bilder und Busten</hi>, by Von M. Hartmann; <hi rend="italic">Diana und Endymion</hi>, by Natalis Victor; and <hi rend="italic">Gedichte, Jubilämus Ausgabe</hi>, by Friedrich Schiller.  
</note>
               <note type="editorial" xml:id="n3" target="r3" n="2">
The English poet Martin Farquhar Tupper (1810-1889) wrote <hi rend="italic">Proverbial Philosophy</hi>,  didactic moral and religious verse published in the mid 1800s.  
</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
