<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="anc.00181">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main" corresp="lg1855">[Review of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1855)]</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            
          <author>
                <choice>
                   <orig>unsigned</orig>
                   <reg>unknown</reg>
                </choice>
             </author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               
               
               
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>The United States Department of Education</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>anc.00181</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain.</p><p>Copyright to footnotes is held by the University of Iowa, and the footnotes are reused here with permission of the University of Iowa.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and is licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of this material should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author key="unknown">
                     <choice><orig>unsigned</orig>
                        <reg>unknown</reg></choice>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">The Merchant's Magazine and Commercial Review</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="1856-05">May 1856</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">34</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="pages">654</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p>The electronic text for this file was prepared by <title level="m">Whitman Archive</title> staff and affiliates, who transcribed the text from a representation of the original (e.g., photocopy, digital scan or other electronic reproduction, microfilm copy). The electronic text was originally prepared in Microsoft Word for submission to the <title level="j">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</title>. The transcription was then exported from Microsoft Word as plain text and encoded for publication on the <title level="m">Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-01-19" who="#el">updated author encoding in TEI header</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2015-10-19">updated rights statement and added encoding description to TEI header</change>
         <change who="#no" when="2015-02-26">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-10-03">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">added note to revisionDesc</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">changed author's name in sourceDesc to last name, first</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2007-07-19">copied and encoded from Word document</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         
            <ab>
               
                   
                     <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>
                   
                   
                      pp. 95.  
                      Brooklyn, New York.  
                   
               
            </ab>
         

         <p>There is the name neither of author nor publisher to this singular book—one of the most singular that has ever come under our notice. Appearing at the first glance to be mere unconnected common-place remarks, aphorisms, and opinions, there is yet developed, on further examination, a vast amount of undisciplined power. Many of the lines are such perfect pictures in themselves, that an artist might draw them without reference to any other material, and produce beautiful pictorial compositions. Other portions of the book are perfectly kaleidoscopic—grotesque changes rapidly succeed each other; and no one save the author himself—and he, perhaps, not an exception—can explain them. Had the elder D'Israeli met with "Leaves of Grass," he would have assuredly included it in his "Curiosities of Literature."<ref target="n1" n="1" xml:id="r1"/> The book is embellished with a portrait (we presume) of the author—a rather melancholy-looking gentleman, with a wide-awake hat on, and neither coat nor vest. Among the "Leaves of Grass," certainly the author himself is not the least remarkable "blade." </p>

      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="notes">
            <p>
               <note type="editorial" target="r1" xml:id="n1" n="1">Isaac D'Israeli, British man of letters and father of the politician Benjamin Disraeli, first published his popular <hi rend="italic">Curiosities of Literature</hi>, consisting of anecdotes, characters, sketches, and observations, literary, critical, and historical in 1791. In the nineteenth century, it was reprinted and expanded multiple times.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
