<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="anc.01069">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main" corresp="lg1867">[Review of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1867)]</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
          <author>
                <choice>
                   <orig>Observer</orig>
                   <reg>unknown</reg>
                </choice>
             </author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               
               
               
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>The United States Department of Education</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>anc.01069</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain.</p><p>The text encoding and annotations were created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and are licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author key="Observer">
                     <choice>
                        <orig>Observer</orig>
                        <reg>unknown</reg>
                     </choice>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">The Massachusetts Weekly Spy</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="1866-11-02">2 November 1866</date>
                     <biblScope unit="pages">1</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
          <p>The electronic text for this file was prepared by <title level="m">Whitman Archive</title> staff, who transcribed the text from a representation of the original (e.g., digital scan or other electronic reproduction, microfilm copy).</p>
       </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
                   <change when="2015-10-19" who="#el">updated rights language and added encoding description in TEI header</change>
         <change who="#no" when="2015-02-26">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2011-10-10">changed Archive ID from anc.00232, since that ID was used for another object</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-10-03">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">added note to revisionDesc</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2007-08-07">copied and encoded from Word document</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head type="main-authorial">WALT WHITMAN.<ref target="n1" n="1" xml:id="r1"/> 
            <!-- [Review of Leaves of Grass (1867)] --> 
         </head>

         <p>My other item relates to one of whose merits as an author opinions  
differ widely.  I refer to Walt Whitman, who has just published  
another edition of his much criticised and remarkable book, "Leaves of  
Grass."  This last volume contains the original poems, with "Drum  
Taps," and some twenty others, later and fresher.  The poet has  
returned to the practice of three centuries since and publishes his  
own works.  This unique and original book can be obtained by  
addressing the author here and enclosing three dollars.  The present  
edition is prefaced with the following "Inscription," which, as it  
gives a glimpse of the philosophy of these poems, and is moreover  
brief, I quote:</p>

         <p>"Small is the theme of the following chaunt, yet the greatest—namely, 
<hi rend="smallcaps">ONE'S SELF</hi>—that wondrous thing, a simple, seperate person.  
That, that for the use of the New World, I sing.</p>
  
         <p>"Man's physiology complete from top to toe, I sing.  Not  
physiognomy alone, nor brain alone is worthy of the muse—I say the  
form is worthier far.  The female form equally with the male, I  
sing Nor cease at the theme of One's Self.  I speak the word of the  
modern, the word <hi rend="smallcaps">EN MASSE</hi>.</p>
  
         <p>"My days I sing, and the lands, with interstice I knew of hapless war.</p>
  
         <p>"O friend, whoe'er you are, at last arriving here to commence, I  
feel through every leaf the pressure of your hand, which I return.   
And thus upon our journey link'd together let us go."</p>

         <p>The arrangement of this new volume will be attractive to those who  
have seen the old.  In connection with the "Good Gray Poet," I am glad  
to mention that the author of that eloquent defence of Mr. Whitman  
against Mr. Harlan's proscription, is quietly resuming his place among  
the literati of the day.  Mr. O'Connor will delight the readers of the  
Galaxy with some charming stories.  Those who remember "The Ghost  
Story" in Putnam, "What Cheer" in Harpers', and his rich and affluent  
romance of "Harrington," will be grateful for this announcement.  Mr.  
O'Connor is reported as preparing a literary lecture, which, if true,  
will be a great treat for those who listen.  There is no young author  
and scholar so eminently adapted to that field as the one of whom I  
write. </p>

         <closer>
            <signed>O<hi rend="smallcaps">BSERVER</hi>.</signed>
         </closer>

      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="notes">

            <p>

               <note type="editorial" target="r1" xml:id="n1" n="1">The <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts Weekly Spy</hi> was published in Worcester. On page 1 is a "Letter from Washington" signed by "Observer."  That letter is divided into several sections, the first couple having to do with the troubles in Baltimore, where there are fears of a new civil war breaking out, followed by an item on Clara Barton, praising her "devotion to the sick and wounded of our armies," and noting she is about to embark on a lecture tour.  Then comes the section called "WALT WHITMAN."</note>

            </p>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
