<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="anc.00191">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main" corresp="lg1860">Walt Whitman's Works</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">[Review of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1860–61)]</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            
          <author>
                <choice>
                   <orig>unsigned</orig>
                   <reg>unknown</reg>
                </choice>
             </author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               
               
               
               
               
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>The United States Department of Education</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain.</p><p>Copyright to footnotes is held by the University of Iowa, and the footnotes are reused here with permission of the University of Iowa.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and is licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of this material should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
            </availability>
         <idno>anc.00191</idno></publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author key="unknown">
                     <choice><orig>unsigned</orig>
                        <reg>unknown</reg></choice>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a">Walt Whitman's Works</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">The London Sunday Times</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="1867-03-03">3 March 1867</date>
                     <biblScope type="pages">7</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p>The electronic text for this file was prepared by <title level="m">Whitman Archive</title> staff and affiliates, who transcribed the text from a representation of the original (e.g., photocopy, digital scan or other electronic reproduction, microfilm copy). The electronic text was originally prepared in Microsoft Word for submission to the <title level="j">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</title>. The transcription was then exported from Microsoft Word as plain text and encoded for publication on the <title level="m">Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-01-19" who="#el">updated author encoding in TEI header</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2015-10-19">updated rights statement and added encoding description to TEI header</change>
         <change who="#no" when="2015-02-26">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-10-03">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">added note to revisionDesc</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">moved bracketed descriptive title to sub title</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">changed author's name in sourceDesc to last name, first</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">fixed capitalization and deleted extraneous punctuation in titleStmt</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2007-07-23">copied and encoded from Word document</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head type="main-authorial">WALT WHITMAN'S WORKS.<hi rend="superscript"><ref>∗</ref></hi> 
            <!-- [Review of Leaves of Grass (1860&#8211;1861)] --> 
         </head>
         <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

         <p>To ninety-nine out of every hundred educated English readers, if not, indeed, to a larger proportion, the name Walt Whitman conveys no meaning or associations whatever. Of the few, moreover, who have previously heard the name still fewer have had the opportunity of seeing the work to which it owes whatever celebrity it may have attained. Yet its bearer is a man of some mark in America, and his work has not only startled the few educated Englishmen who have seen it, but is undoubtedly destined to hold a prominent position in American literature. Many causes contribute to render <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, as Walt Whitman's principal work is called, a sealed book to English readers. The first reason is its costliness. A dozen copies would scarcely, we should suppose, reward the most diligent search that could be instituted through England, and, probably, not a quarter of that number is on sale. When met with at the establishments of the principal American bookselling agents, the price of the volume is as much as is asked for the complete works of Tennyson or Swinburne. A second reason for the scarcity of the book is that the form of its composition is not at first glance attractive, and that its contents are such as cannot possibly be admitted into family reading. <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, is, however, the most thoroughly national and characteristic American poem that has yet seen the light, and is a work the influence of which will yet be felt. It is a book concerning which Englishmen ought to know at least a little. For various reasons, then, among which figures prominently the difficulty in obtaining the volume, we hold we are rendering a real service to our readers in bringing under their observation a few striking features in this remarkable and most suggestive work.</p>

         <p>We have spoken of it as national and characteristic in the fullest sense, and so it is. An Englishman might have written ninety-nine hundredths of American poetry. Scarcely a line or stanza in Longfellow, Holmes, Bryant, Whittier, that is in the fullest sense American. The philosophical poems of Emerson have a flavour of nationality, and a very strong taste thereof pervades such comic works as the Big[e]low papers, and other similar productions. But those comic works which aim at satirising the manners and customs of every-day life are necessarily the first parts of a young nation's literature, in which local colour is observable. Before the appearance of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, no serious American work was wholly or in any wide sense national. The spirit that pervades <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> is essentially American. It is more. To use a word the author is fond of, it is Manhattanese. A resident in the capital of the Empire State alone could have produced it. The rowdyism and greed of New York life, as well as its higher qualities, pervade it. Walt Whitman is as completely a New Yorkist as Charles Lamb was a Londoner or Christopher North a Scot. Not that he is uninfluenced by preceding writers of other countries. On the contrary, his work is, to some extent, an <hi rend="italic">olla podrida</hi> of other people's thoughts, manners, and forms, but the main current belongs to New York.<ref target="n2" n="1" xml:id="r2"/>  The philosophy and theology are decidedly American, the ethics are altogether of New York. We seem to trace half-a-dozen authors in Walt Whitman. The freedom and coarseness of his phraseology recal[l] Rabelais. In his most poetical passages he reminds us of Ossian. His philosophy has a flavour of Emerson; his constant display of independence and his peculiar habit of self-assertion, find no parallel save in George Wither; and his didactic breathings are in form, if in nothing else, at times suggestive of Tupper.<ref target="n3" n="2" xml:id="r3"/>
         </p> 
	
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> is a volume of nearly five hundred pages, of what the author considers and calls poetry. It is divided under several heads, the most important of which are "Walt Whitman," "Chants Democratic," "Leaves of Grass" (which gives its title to the whole), "Enfans d'Adam," "Calamus," and "Messenger Leaves." All are alike in shape. Though called poems, the contents of the entire volume, one short passage in which the rhyme may be the result of accident excepted, have neither rhyme nor metre. The poems have a long rhythmic flow, which bears about the same relation to ordinary poetry that the military or mournful music of a savage tribe does to music as understood in Western Europe. The verses are of unequal length, ordinarily possessing a caesura and a strongly-marked accent on the penultimate syllable. This last quality is, however, not always observable. To quit form, however, and come to what is more important, matter, there are three pervading ideas in the volume, which may be described as the apotheosis of the flesh, the exaltation of states life, and the promotion of comradeship. To deal with these <hi rend="italic">seriatim</hi>, in the first Whitman takes part in a natural and easily comprehensible reaction, signs of which have of late manifested themselves, against the extreme glorification of the soul at the expense of the body, which has been one of the results of Christianity.<ref target="n4" n="3" xml:id="r4"/> Heathen teaching held soul and body of equal account, and the Greek regarding each with equal reverence, was at as much pains to cultivate the powers of the one as is the other. The belief in the equality of the body with the soul largely pervades the writings of Whitman. Next to this comes his exaltation of democracy in general, and of American democracy in particular. Lastly comes the notion of comradeship. This last we only partially understand, and are not in the least tempted to enter upon. These are the views which first recal[l] themselves upon rising from the accomplished perusal of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. A hundred other points, however, require mentioning ere we can profess to bring before the reader Walt Whitman as he really is. It is time, however, to give the reader a few quotations illustrative of the author's modes of thought. Fortunately, in so doing we give an insight into the nature of his verse also. We are obliged to be guarded in our selections. It is not possible to quote the passages which are in the fullest sense characteristic. Neither is it possible in the space we have allotted ourselves to give more than the feeblest conceivable idea of the nature of the contents of the remarkable book before us. Here are four lines in which the author describes himself:—</p>

         <!-- From the poem "Walt Whitman" (later: "Song of Myself"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00048" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"Walt Whitman, an American, one of the roughs, a kosmos.</l>
                        <l>Disorderly, fleshy, sensual, eating, drinking, breeding,</l>
                        <l>No sentimentalist—no stander above men and women, or apart <lb/>from men,</l>
                        <l>No more modest than immodest."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>He continues with wonderful worship of himself in lines from which we extract almost at random:—</p>

         <!-- From the poem "Walt Whitman" (later: "Song of Myself"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00048" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"I dote on myself—there is that lot of me, and all so luscious,</l>
                        <l>Each moment and whatever happens thrills me with delight.</l>
                        <l>O, I am so wonderful!</l>
                        <l>I cannot tell how my ankles bend, nor whence the causes of my <lb/>faintest wish,</l>
                        <l>Nor the cause of the friendship I emit, not the cause of the <choice><orig>friend-<lb/>ship</orig><reg>friendship</reg></choice> I take again.</l>
                        <l>That I walk up my stoop, I pause to consider if it really be.</l>
                        <l>That I eat and drink is spectacle enough for the great authors <lb/>and school.</l>
                        <l>A morning glory at my window satisfies me more than the <choice><orig>meta-<lb/>physics</orig><reg>metaphysics</reg></choice> of books."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>
	
         <p>His general views may be gathered from one or two passage selected as illustrative of different phases of mind:—</p>

         <!-- From the poem "Walt Whitman" (later: "Song of Myself"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00048" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"I play not here marches for victors only; I play great marches <lb/>for conquered and slain persons.</l>
                        <l>Have you heard that it was good to gain the day?</l>
                        <l>I also say that it is good to fall—battles are lost in the same spirit in <lb/>which they are won.</l>
                        <l>I beat triumphal drums for the dead.</l>
                        <l>I blow through my embouchures my loudest and gayest music to <lb/>them.</l>
                        <l>Vivas to those who have failed.</l>
                        <l>And to those whose war vessels sunk in the sea;</l>
                        <l>And those themselves who sank in the sea;</l>
                        <l>And to all generals that have lost engagements; and all <choice><orig>over-<lb/>come</orig><reg>overcome</reg></choice> heroes;</l>
                        <l>And the numberless unknown heroes, equal to the greatest heroes <lb/>known."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

	
         <p>His transcendentalism finds vent in the lines in which, after praising the discoveries of Positive science and singing hurra for all exact demonstrators, he continues:—</p>

         <!-- From the poem "Walt Whitman" (later: "Song of Myself"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00048" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"Gentlemen, I receive you and attach and clasp hands with <lb/>you.</l>
                        <l>The facts are useful and real—they are not my dwelling—I enter <lb/>by them to an area of the dwelling."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>His theology is continually obtruded:—</p>

         <!-- From the poem "Walt Whitman" (later: "Song of Myself"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00048" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"I do not despise you priests.</l>
                        <l>My faith is the greatest of faiths and the least of faiths,</l>
                        <l>Enclosing all worship, ancient and modern, and all between <lb/>ancient and modern."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>Or again:— </p>

         <!-- From the poem "Walt Whitman" (later: "Song of Myself"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00048" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"And I call to mankind, be not curious about God,</l> 
                        <l>For I, who am curious about each, am not curious about God.</l> 
                        <l>No array of terms can say how much I am at peace about God <lb/>and about death.</l>
                        <l>I hear and behold God in every object, yet understand God not <lb/>in the least.</l> 
                        <l>Why should I wish to see God better than this day?</l> 
                        <l>I see something of God each hour of the twenty-four, and each <lb/>moment then.</l> 
                        <l>In the faces of men and women I see God, and in my own face <lb/>in the glass.</l> 
                        <l>I find letters from God dropped in the street, and every one is <lb/>signed by God's name.</l>
                        <l>And I leave them where they are, for I know that they will <choice><orig>punc-<lb/>tually</orig><reg>punctually</reg></choice> come for ever and ever.</l>
                        <l>And as to you Death, and you bitter hug of mortality, it is idle to <lb/>try to alarm me."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>Again:—</p>

         <!-- From "Leaves of Grass" No.2, Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00436" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"I do not understand the realities of death, but I know they are <lb/>great.</l>
                        <l>I do not understand the least reality of life; how, then, can I <choice><orig>un-<lb/>derstand</orig><reg>understand</reg></choice> the realities of death?'</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>The "Chants Democratic" exalt everything American, the attributes of people and country alike, and are full of truly American exaggeration. They are far less interesting to English readers than the other portions of the volume. Everything American is the subject of his praises:— </p>

         <!-- From "Chants Democratic" No. 1 (later: "By Blue Ontario's Shore"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00221" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"These states are the amplest poem.</l> 
                        <l>Here is not merely a nation, but a teeming nation of nations.</l> 
                        <l>Here the doings of men correspond with the broadcast doings of <lb/>the day and night.</l>
                        <l>Here is what moves in magnificent masses—carelessly faithful <lb/>of particulars.</l>
                        <l>Here are the roughs, beards, friendliness, combativeness, the <lb/>soul loves,"</l>
                        <l>Here the flowing trains—here the crowds, equality, diversity, the <lb/>soul loves."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>He sings the American wherever he is found:—</p>

         <!-- From "Chants Democratic" No. 2 (later: "Song of the Broad-Axe"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00116" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"Cutters down of wood and haulers of it to the Penobscot or <lb/>Kennebec,</l>
                        <l>Dwellers in cabins among the California mountains or by the <lb/>little lakes or on the Columbia.</l>
                        <l>Dwellers south on the banks of the Gila or Rio Grande—friendly <lb/>gatherings, the characters and fun,</l>
                        <l>Dwellers up north in Minnesota and by the Yellow Stone River— <lb/>dwellers on coasts and off coasts, etc"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>But we can extract no more. Our space forbids, and, inadequately as our task is accomplished, we must retire from it. Our readers have seen enough of the book to have an idea of it and the author. To know all his talent and eccentricity is impossible till the book itself has been perused. The contents of the volume can by a stretch only be called poetry. They lack its first and most indispensable element, beauty. They are, however, strange and most suggestive reading, and such as a man of culture will not care entirely to ignore. Spite of barbarous expressions, vile Americanisms, and all faults of thought and expression, the writings of Walt Whitman are full of character, and well worthy of contemplation. They will in time attain a certain measure of celebrity even, and their author is surely entitled to a distinct niche in American literature. With this short notice we dismiss him as he dismisses himself—</p>

         <!-- From the poem "Walt Whitman" (later: "Song of Myself"), Leaves of Grass 1860-61 --> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00048" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup"> 
                        <l>"I bequeath myself to the dirt, to grow from the grass I love,</l>
                        <l>If you want me again look for me under your boot soles."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>Meantime, we hope, we have brought him before the reader as he stands—</p>

         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="printed">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00048" cert="absolute"/>
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"Sounding his barbaric yawp over the roofs of the world."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-left"/>

         
            
            <ab><hi rend="superscript">∗</hi>
               
                   
                     <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>
                   
                   
                      
                        <hi rend="italic">Boston:</hi>
                      
                      
                        <hi rend="italic">Thayer and Eldridge</hi>. 
                      
                        <hi rend="italic">London:</hi>
                      
                      
                        <hi rend="italic">Trübner and Co.</hi>
                      
                   
               
            </ab>
         

      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="notes">

            <p>
               <note type="editorial" target="r2" xml:id="n2" n="1">A spicy stew (originally from Spain or Portugal).</note>

               <note type="editorial" target="r3" xml:id="n3" n="2">George Wither, seventeenth-century British poet who dedicated a book of satires to himself. Martin Farquhar Tupper was a popular British poet who wrote religious and philosophical free verse.</note>

               <note type="editorial" target="r4" xml:id="n4" n="3">Possibly a reference to "muscular Christianity," a movement to counter the traditional elevation of soul over body by emphasizing manly athleticism. It first appeared in Britain under this name in the late 1850s and quickly spread to the United States.</note>
            </p>

         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>