<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="anc.02132">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main" corresp="boughs">Walt Whitman's Book</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            
          <author>W. M. Payne</author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>The United States Department of Education</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2018</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain.</p><p>The text encoding and annotations were created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and are licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
            </availability>
         <idno>anc.02132</idno></publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author key="Payne, W. M.">W. M. Payne</author>
                  <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman's Book</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Chicago Evening Journal</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="1889-03-16">16 March 1889</date>
                     <biblScope type="pages">[unknown]</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
          <p>The electronic text for this file was prepared by <title level="m">Whitman Archive</title> staff, who transcribed the text from a representation of the original (e.g., digital scan or other electronic reproduction, microfilm copy).</p>
       </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#km" when="2018-08-20">corrected typo</change>
         <change who="#km" when="2018-08-16">fixed links in footnotes</change>
         <change who="#km" when="2018-08-01">copied from correspondence file loc.03489</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         
         <head type="main-authorial">WALT WHITMAN'S BOOK</head>
         
         <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

         <head type="sub">A Striking Collection of Essays and
            Poems—A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads.</head>
         
         <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

         <head type="sub">The Soul of Eastern Civilization—A
            Suggestive Work by Percival Lowell—Review of Minor Publications.</head>
         
         <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
         
         <head type="sub">Walt Whitman.</head>
         
         <p>The time is past when Walt Whitman could be dismissed
            with a smile or a sneer, and he has already taken his place in the foremost rank
            of our writers. The public has been slow to recognize the power and value of his
            work, but no public, possessed of any degree of intelligence, could long hold
            out against the verdict rendered in his favor by the consensus of English and
            American critics. No writer of ordinary powers could win the approval and praise
            of such men (to name but a few) as Tennyson,<ref target="n1" xml:id="r1" n="1"/> Swinburne,<ref target="n2" xml:id="r2" n="2"/> W. M. Rossetti,<ref target="n3" xml:id="r3" n="3"/> J. A. Symonds<ref target="n4" xml:id="r4" n="4"/> and E. C. Stedman,<ref target="n5" xml:id="r5" n="5"/> and this praise and
            this approval have been bestowed by them in generous measure. It will appear
            then, at the present day, neither paradox nor extravagance to say that "November
            Boughs" (Philadelphia: David McKay)<ref target="n6" xml:id="r6" n="6"/> is an important
            permanent contribution to American literature.</p>
         
         <p>The contents of this suggestively named volume are
            diversified. There are some twenty pages of poems, half a dozen essays in
            literary criticism, several miscellaneous prose papers, and much fragmentary
            reminiscence of a varied and well-spent life. Of most interest, perhaps, is the
            "Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads," which serves as the volume's preface. In
            this admirable paper the veteran poet, with the objective vision of age, takes a
            long retrospective survey of his activities, admitting the reader more closely
            than before into the secret of his endeavor, and giving clear and forcible
            expression to the aims for whose accomplishment he has striven. "At the age of
            31 to 33," he tell us, he found himself possessed by an overmastering impulse.
            "This was a feeling or ambition to articulate and faithfully express in literary
            and poetic form, and uncompromisingly, my own physical, emotional, moral,
            intellectual and esthetic Personality, in the midst of, and tallying the
            momentous spirit and facts of its immediate days, and of current
            America—and to exploit that Personality, identified with place and date,
            in a far more candid and comprehensive sense than any hitherto poem or book."
            The outcome of this ambition was the collection of pieces known collectively as
            "Leaves of Grass" and the prose papers also put forth from time to time. "The
            best comfort of the whole business is that, unstopp'd and unwarped by any
            influence outside the soul within me, I have had my say entirely my own way, and
            put it unerringly on record." This is what he tells us, with a pride as
            pardonable as the occasion for its exhibition is rare even among writers of more
            than usual sincerity and earnestness of purpose. In another place the feeling of
            pride leads to this exclamation: "My Book and I—what a period we have
            presumed to span! those thirty years from 1850 to 1880—and America in
            them! Proud, proud indeed may we be if we have culled enough of that period in
            its own spirit to worthily waft a few live breaths of it to the future!"</p>
         
         <p>Upon the two matters in which Whitman's work has
            mainly given offence—its disregard respectively of the conventional
            requirements of morality and of literary form—this introduction is clear
            and outspoken. Concerning the latter of these matters we read: "I know well
            enough, too, that in respect to pictorial talent, dramatic situations, and
            especially in verbal melody and all the conventional technique of poetry, not
            only the divine works, that to-day stand ahead in the world's reading, but
            dozens more, transcend (some of them immeasurably transcend) all I have done or
            could do. But it seemed to me, as the objects in Nature, the themes of
            estheticism, and all special exploitations of the mind and soul, involve not
            only their own inherent quality, but the quality, just as inherent and
            important, of <hi rend="italic">their point of view</hi>, the time had come to
            reflect all themes and things, old and new, in the lights thrown on them by the
            advent of America and democracy—to chant those themes through the
            utterance of one not only the grateful and reverent legatee of the past, but the
            born child of the New World—to illustrate all through the genesis and
            ensemble of to-day; and that such illustration and ensemble are the chief
            demands of America's prospective imaginative literature." While this plea may by
            no means be accepted as justifying Whitman's literary form, which has faults of
            which his defective sense does not allow him to dream, it is valuable as a
            statement of his aim in writing, and for its hearty recognition of the
            conventional types of excellence in literary composition. This recognition,
            indeed, finds further and ample expression in the papers on Tennyson, Burns and
            Shakspeare which are given in the present volume. Of the real purpose of
            literature, whether conventional or not in form, Whitman is substantially at one
            with all the great writers from Shakspeare downwards. "I say the profoundest
            service that poems or any other writings can do for their reader is not merely
            to satisfy the intellect or supply something polished and interesting, nor even
            to depict great passions or persons and events, but to fill him with vigorous
            and clean manliness, religiousness, and give him <hi rend="italic">good
               heart</hi> as a radical possession and habit." These words are as noble as
            they are profoundly true.</p>
         
         <p>The other matter, brought into prominence by the
            moralists, who have made themselves mainly responsible for the tardiness of the
            recognition bestowed upon Whitman's work, is thus met, and the opinion is
            enforced by years of careful reflection. "From another point of view, 'Leaves of
            Grass' is avowedly the song of Sex and Amativeness, and even
            Animality—though meanings that do not usually go along with these words
            are behind all, and will duly emerge; and all are sought to be lifted into a
            different light and atmosphere. Of this feature, intentionally palpable in a few
            lines, I shall only say the espousing principle of those lines so gives breath
            of life to my whole scheme that the bulk of the pieces might as well have been
            left unwritten were those lines omitted. Difficult as it will be, it has become,
            in my opinion, imperative to achieve a shifted attitude from superior men and women
            toward the thought and fact of sexuality as an element in character,
            personality, the emotions, and a theme in literature. I am not going to argue
            the question by itself; it does not stand by itself. . . . In respect to
            editions of 'Leaves of Grass' in time to come (if there should be such), I take
            occasion now to confirm those lines with the settled convictions and deliberate
            renewals of thirty years, and I hereby prohibit, as far as word of mine can do,
            any elision of them." </p>
         
         <p>The few pages of poetry included within this volume
            should be reckoned with Whitman's most remarkable work. They exhibit, of course,
            the peculiarities of diction and the general formlessness of the "Leaves of
            Grass." The reader who is not prepared to accept the writer's theories, or,
            rather, who is not willing to acquiesce in them for the time being, will not be
            appealed to by these "Sands at Seventy." Admitting the peculiarities as a
            constant and consistent factor, there is much that is both striking and fine.
            Take, for example, this epigram on "The Bravest Soldiers:"</p>
         
         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <l>"Brave, brave were the soldiers (high-named to-day) who lived through the
               night;</l>
            <l>But the bravest press'd to the front and fell, unnamed, unkown."</l>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>
         
         <p>Here is a touch of nature that is admirable in its
            thought and feeling:</p>
         
         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <l>"Simple and fresh and fair from
            Winter's close emerging,</l>
            <l>As if no artifice of fashion, business, politics, had ever been.</l>
            <l>Forth from its sunny nook of shelter'd grass—innocent, golden, calm as
               the dawn,</l>
            <l>The Spring's first dandelion shows its trustful face."</l>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>
         
         <p>The following fragment is based upon an incident of
            the Greely expedition—the hearing of a solitary snow-bird's song by the
            explorers in 83 degrees of north latitude:</p>
         
         <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <l>"Of that blithe throat of thine from Arctic bleak and blank,</l>
            <l>I'll mind the lesson, solitary bird—let me, too, welcome chilling
               drifts,</l>
            <l>E'en the profoundest chill, as now—a torpid pulse, a brain
               unnerv'd,</l>
            <l>Old age land-lock'd within its Winter bay—(cold, cold, O cold!)</l>
            <l>These snowy hairs, my feeble arm, my frozen feet,</l>
            <l>For them thy faith, thy role I take, and grave it to the last;</l>
            <l>Not summer's zones alone—not chants of youth, or south's warm tides
               alone,</l>
            <l>But held by sluggish toes, pack'd in the northern ice, the cumulus of
               years,</l>
            <l>These with gay heart I also sing."</l>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>
         
         <p>There is something haunting about these lines, with
            whatever species of composition we may choose to class them, and this haunting
            quality appears upon every one of the too few pages which contain the poet's
            latest songs. At his best, Whitman has a genius for style and for apt expression
            of thought which allies him with the greater poets and insures for him the
            recognition and the respect of the future.</p>

      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="notes">
            <p>
               <note type="editorial" xml:id="n1" target="r1" n="1">
                  Alfred, Lord Tennyson (1809–1892) succeeded
                  William Wordsworth as poet laureate of Great Britain in 1850. The intense male
                  friendship described in <hi rend="italic">In Memoriam</hi>, which Tennyson wrote
                  after the death of his friend Arthur Henry Hallam, possibly influenced Whitman's
                  poetry. Tennyson began a correspondence with Whitman on <ref target="../../../biography/correspondence/tei/med.00410">July 12, 1871</ref>. Although Tennyson extended an invitation for Whitman
                  to visit England, Whitman never acted on the offer.
               </note>
               <note type="editorial" xml:id="n2" target="r2" n="2">
                  Algernon Charles Swinburne (1837–1909) was a
                  British poet, critic, playwright, and novelist. He was also one of Whitman's
                  earliest English admirers. At the conclusion of <hi rend="italic">William Blake:
                     A Critical Essay</hi> (1868), 300–303, Swinburne pointed out
                  similarities between Whitman and Blake, and praised "Out of the Cradle Endlessly
                  Rocking" and "When Lilacs Last in the Dooryard Bloom'd," which he termed "the
                  most sweet and sonorous nocturn ever chanted in the church of the world." His
                  famous lyric "To Walt Whitman in America" is included in <hi rend="italic">Songs
                     before Sunrise</hi> (1871). For the story of Swinburne's veneration of
                  Whitman and his later recantation, see two essays by Terry L. Meyers, "<ref target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/criticism/wwqr/pdf/anc.00740.pdf">Swinburne and Whitman: Further Evidence</ref>," <hi rend="italic">Walt
                        Whitman Quarterly Review</hi> 14 (Summer 1996), 1–11 and "<ref target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/criticism/wwqr/pdf/anc.00902.pdf">A
                           Note on Swinburne and Whitman</ref>," <hi rend="italic">WWQR</hi> 21 (Summer
                  2003), 38–39.
               </note>
               <note type="editorial" xml:id="n3" target="r3" n="3">
                  William Michael Rossetti (1829–1915), brother
                  of Dante Gabriel and Christina Rossetti, was an English editor and a champion of
                  Whitman's work. In 1868 Rossetti edited Whitman's <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>,
                  selected from the 1867 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. Whitman referred
                  to Rossetti's edition as a "horrible dismemberment of my book" in his <ref target="../../../biography/correspondence/tei/loc.01696">August 12, 1871</ref>, letter to F.S. Ellis. Nonetheless,
                  the edition provided a major boost to Whitman's reputation, and Rossetti would
                  remain a staunch supporter for the rest of Whitman's life, drawing in
                  subscribers to the 1876 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> and fundraising
                  for Whitman in England. For more on Whitman's relationship with Rossetti, see
                  Sherwood Smith, "<ref target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/criticism/current/encyclopedia/entry_48.html">Rossetti, William Michael (1829–1915)</ref>," <hi rend="italic">Walt
                        Whitman: An Encyclopedia</hi>, ed. J.R. LeMaster and Donald D. Kummings (New
                  York: Garland Publishing, 1998).
               </note>
               <note type="editorial" xml:id="n4" target="r4" n="4">
                  John Addington Symonds (1840–1893), a
                  prominent biographer, literary critic, and poet in Victorian England, was author
                  of the seven-volume history <hi rend="italic">Renaissance in Italy</hi>, as well
                  as <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman—A Study</hi> (1893), and a translator of
                  Michelangelo's sonnets. But in the smaller circles of the emerging upper-class
                  English homosexual community, he was also well known as a writer of homoerotic
                  poetry and a pioneer in the study of homosexuality, or sexual inversion as it
                  was then known. See Andrew Higgins, "<ref target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/criticism/current/encyclopedia/entry_56.html">Symonds, John Addington [1840–1893]</ref>," <hi rend="italic">Walt
                        Whitman: An Encyclopedia</hi>, ed. J.R. LeMaster and Donald D. Kummings (New
                  York: Garland Publishing, 1998).
               </note>
               <note type="editorial" xml:id="n5" target="r5" n="5">
                  Edmund Clarence Stedman
                  (1833–1908) was a man of diverse talents. He edited for a year the <hi rend="italic">Mountain County Herald</hi> at Winsted, Connecticut, wrote
                  "Honest Abe of the West," presumably Lincoln's first campaign song, and served
                  as correspondent of the <hi rend="italic">New York World</hi> from 1860 to 1862.
                  In 1862 and 1863 he was a private secretary in the Attorney General's office
                  until he entered the firm of Samuel Hallett and Company in September, 1863. The
                  next year he opened his own brokerage office. He published many volumes of poems
                  and was an indefatigable compiler of anthologies, among which were <hi rend="italic">Poets of America</hi>, 2 vols. (Boston: Houghton Mifflin,
                  1885) and <hi rend="italic">A Library of American Literature from the Earliest
                     Settlement to the Present Time</hi>, 11 vols. (New York: C. L. Webster,
                  1889–90). For more, see Donald Yannella, "<ref target="http://whitmanarchive.org/criticism/current/encyclopedia/entry_107.html">Stedman, Edmund Clarence (1833–1908)</ref>," <hi rend="italic">Walt
                        Whitman: An Encyclopedia</hi>, ed. J.R. LeMaster and Donald D. Kummings (New
                  York: Garland Publishing, 1998).
               </note>
               <note type="editorial" xml:id="n6" target="r6" n="6">
                  David McKay (1860–1918) took
                  over Philadelphia-based publisher Rees Welsh's bookselling and publishing
                  businesses in 1881–2. McKay and Rees Welsh published the 1881 edition of
                  <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> after opposition from the Boston
                  District Attorney prompted James R. Osgood &amp; Company of Boston, the
                  publisher Whitman had originally contracted with for publication of the volume,
                  to withdraw. McKay also went on to publish <hi rend="italic">Specimen Days &amp;
                     Collect</hi>, <hi rend="italic">November Boughs</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Gems
                        from Walt Whitman</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Complete Prose Works</hi>. For
                  more information about McKay, see Joel Myerson, "<ref target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/criticism/current/encyclopedia/entry_88.html">McKay, David (1860–1918)</ref>," <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman: An
                        Encyclopedia</hi>, ed. J.R. LeMaster and Donald D. Kummings (New York:
                  Garland Publishing, 1998).
               </note>
               
            </p>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>       
</TEI>