<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="anc.00088">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main" corresp="lg1881">[Review of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1881–82)]</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            
          <author>
                <choice>
                   <orig>unsigned</orig>
                   <reg>unknown</reg>
                </choice>
             </author>
            <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               
               
               
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ts">Todd Stabley</persName>
               
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>The United States Department of Education</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and is licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of this material should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
            </availability>
         <idno>anc.00088</idno></publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author key="unknown">
                     <choice><orig>unsigned</orig>
                        <reg>unknown</reg></choice>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">The Detroit Free Press</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="1882-01-07">7 January 1882</date>
                     <biblScope unit="pages">3</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
          <p>The original electronic text for this file was prepared for Walt Whitman, <title level="m">The Contemporary Reviews</title>, ed. Kenneth M. Price (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996), and the transcription was completed by consulting a representation of the original (e.g., photocopy, microfilm copy). Following publication of that volume, Price received an updated transcription file from Cambridge University Press, and the <title level="m">Whitman Archive</title> has used the final file from the publisher as the basis for the electronic text presented here.</p>
          </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-01-19" who="#el">updated author encoding in TEI header</change>
                   <change when="2015-10-19" who="#el">updated rights language and added encoding description in TEI header</change>
         <change who="#no" when="2015-02-26">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-10-03">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">added note to revisionDesc</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2007-12-18">changed author's name in sourceDesc to last name, first</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2007-07-18">"purified" xml; copy-edited transcription and made changes as
necessary</change>
         <change who="#ts" when="2006-01-17">Encoded, validated</change>
         
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         
         
            <ab>
               
                   L<hi rend="smallcaps">EAVES OF</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">RASS</hi>
                   
                  By Walt Whitman. 
                   
                      Boston:  
                      James B. Osgood &amp; Co.  
                      Detroit:  
                      Thorndike Nourse.  
                   
               
            </ab>
         


         <p>That Walt Whitman is genuine and thoroughly believes in himself is beyond question. It does not therefore follow that he is a poet, though we have noticed that those who insist most strenuously upon his claim to be so considered, base the claim mainly on his genuineness and self-confidence, waiving for the moment all discussion as to the beastliness of certain of his verses—there really is no other word which fitly characterizes them—his poems, so-called, very rarely furnish any excuse for their appearance in the poetic form. There is no rhyme or pretense of any, nor is there any attempt at meter. With one or two exceptions they might just as well be written like other prose.</p> 

         <p>Of course this does not settle the question. There is a great deal of poetry in the English language without either rhyme or meter. But it is recognized as such in spite of the prosaic form; while Walt Whitman's ebullitions, if put in that form, would not be. Printed as prose they would strike the reader as grandiloquent, sonorous, rhetorical, sometimes as imaginative, almost always as egotistical, but very rarely as poetical. Take, for example, such a verse as the following, strike out the misplaced capitals and the spaces, in short, print it as prose is printed, and see how much of the "divine afflatus" can be detected in it:</p> 

         <q who="Walt Whitman">
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <lg type="poem">
                     <relations>
                        <work ref="xxx.00271" cert="absolute"/>
                        <!-- from Faces -->
                     </relations>
                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>Sauntering the pavement or riding the country by <lb/>road, lo, such faces!</l>
                        <l>Faces of friendship, precision, caution, suavity, <lb/>ideality,</l>
                        <l>The spiritual prescient face, the always welcome <lb/>common benevolent face.</l>
                        <l>The face of the singing of music,the grand faces <lb/>of natural lawyers and judges, broad at the <lb/>back-top.</l>
                        <l>The faces of hunters and fishers, bulged at the <lb/>brows, the shaved,blanched faces of <choice><orig>ortho-<lb/>dox</orig><reg>orthodox</reg></choice> citizens.</l>
                        <l>The pure, extravagant, yearning, questioning <lb/>artist's face.</l>
                        <l>The ugly face of some beautiful soul,the <choice><orig>hand-<lb/>some</orig><reg>handsome</reg></choice>, detested or despised face.</l>
                     </lg>

                     <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>This now is too lamentable a face for a man.</l>
                        <l>Some abject louse asking leave to be,cringing for <lb/>it,</l>
                        <l>Some milk-nosed maggot blessing what lets it wrig <lb/>to its hole.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </q>

         <p>As for the beastly portion of the volume,"The Children of Adam," it is an outrage upon the decencies of literature. It is open, undisguised sensualism of the grossest sort; and its publication is a grave mistake. We have no special fear that it will corrupt the rising generation, for its indecency is so potent that intelligent parents and guardians will look out for it. But when such a work, with the imprint of a highly respected publishing house, has free circulation and transmission through the mails, an argument almost unanswerable is furnished for the professional perverters of youth whose vile trash, heretofore excluded from the mails, is really less indecorous in form—whatever it may be in spirit—than some portions of "Leaves of Grass."</p> 


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>