<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="anc.01071">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main" corresp="poems">The Poems of Walt Whitman</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">[Review of <hi rend="italic">Poems by Walt Whitman</hi>]</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>
                    <choice>
                        <orig>W. H.</orig>
                        <reg>William Howitt</reg>
                    </choice>
                </author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kp">Ken Price</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>anc.01071</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain.</p><p>The text encoding and annotations were created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and are licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author key="Howitt, William">
                            <choice>
                                <orig>W. H.</orig>
                                <reg>William Howitt</reg>
                            </choice>
                        </author>
                        <title level="a">The Poems of Walt Whitman</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Spiritual Magazine</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
                            <date xml:id="dat1" cert="high" when="1870-09">September 1870</date>
                            <biblScope type="pages">34-40</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
</biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
          <p>The electronic text for this file was prepared by <title level="m">Whitman Archive</title> staff, who transcribed the text from a representation of the original (e.g., digital scan or other electronic reproduction, microfilm copy).</p>
       </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-01-19" who="#el">updated author encoding in TEI header</change>
                   <change when="2015-10-19" who="#el">updated rights language and added encoding description in TEI header</change>
            <change when="2012-10-31" who="#jc">fixed typos and other minor encoding issues</change>
            <change when="2012-10-30" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-12-05" who="#al">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2011-11-01" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-10-29" who="#kb">revised</change>
            <change when="2011-10-27" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-10-25" who="#kb">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="ancillary">
        <body>

            <head type="main-authorial">The Poems of Walt Whitman</head>

           <div1 type="section"> <p>The poems of Walt Whitman have been much praised and wondered at in this country
                since they were published here by Tr&#252;bner and by Hotten, but though they are of the
                most decidedly and avowedly spiritualistic character, nobody seems to see that fact.
                They are in a singular, unrhymed style; sometimes in irregular hexameters, sometimes
                in the Ossianic metre, sometimes in that of <hi rend="italic">Hiawatha</hi>,
                sometimes absolutely prosaic, but always original and audaciously American. We do
                not rate him, like one of his editors here, as one of the greatest poets that ever
                lived, but he is unquestionably a great and original poet. He sets all
                conventionality at defiance. He is as free in his style, his thoughts, his
                sentiments, as the most Yankee and pretentious of his countrymen. His brag about the
                Great Republic and everything belonging to the States is of the most preposterous
                and laughable kind. His exuberance of imagery, his cataloguings of everything that
                comes in his head of every possible thing in this globe, or in the universe, is
                frequently oppressive; but amidst all this extravagance, verbiage, and tautology
                there rises a continual stream of the brightest new thoughts, the tenderest and most
                dewy sentiments and kindly human feelings, like the cool and rapid rushing of a
                mountain-born river beneath the green boughs of the forest or through the flowery
                grass of the summer meadow. The character of the philosophy of these poems, however,
                is what we desire now particularly to call attention to. It is of that advanced and
                transcendental kind which belongs only to writers who have been baptized into the
                true Jordan of Spiritualism, and have ascended from its banks into the borders of
                the Summer Land, walking there with ever-increasing wonder, and bringing thence the
                flowers and fruits of a new and eternal promise; grapes of the true vine; and golden
                gatherings from the trees of both knowledge and life. All such visitors of the world
                beyond come back with a newness of aspect, of manner, of speech, and tone of mind,
                that are unmistakable. We know them at once by the eye beaming with the light that
                shines on the mountains of the imperishable; by the joy that flushes the features of
                those who have walked and talked with the angels; by the broad spirit of sympathy
                which brings to the earth the illimitable fervour of the heavens, and sees in the
                smallest thing, in the humblest mortal, the signs of the wonder-working of the
                Infinite Spirit of creative and supporting Love. This is what we see at once in the
                poems of Walt Whitman: and he at once responds to our challenge, "Poet, thou art
                one of us!" with these words:</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <l>As for me (torn, stormy, even as I, amid these vehement days;)</l>
                            <l>I have the idea of all and am all, and believe in all:</l>
                            <l>I believe Materialism is true, and Spiritualism is true&#8212;I
                                reject no part.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>Nor do we: Materialism is as true as Spiritualism when it is united to Spiritualism;
                it is false, or rather defective only, when it is a mere part.</p>

            <p>In a succeeding poem, we have him clearly in trance, and the impressing spirit
                speaking through him:&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>Take my hand, Walt Whitman!</l>
                                <l>Such gliding wonders! such sights and sounds!</l>
                                <l>Such joined unended links, each hooked to the next!</l>
                                <l>Each answering all&#8212;each sharing the earth with all.</l>
                            </lg>

                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>What widens within you, Walt Whitman?</l>
                                <l>What waves and soils exuding?</l>
                                <l>What climes? what persons and lands are here?</l>
                                <l>Who are the infants? some playing, some slumbering?</l>
                                <l>Who are the girls? who are the married women?</l>
                                <l>Who are the three old men going slowly with their arms about each
                                    other's necks?</l>
                                <l>What rivers are these? what forests and fruits are these?</l>
                                <l>What are the mountains called that rise so high in the mists?</l>
                                <l>What myriads of dwellings are they, filled with dwellers?</l>
                            </lg>

                            <lg type="lingroup">
                                <l>Within me latitude widens, longitude lengthens;</l>
                                <l>Asia, Africa, Europe, are to the east&#8212;America is provided
                                    for in the west:</l>
                                <l>Banding the bulge of the earth winds the hot equator;</l>
                                <l>Curiously north and south turn the axis-ends;</l>
                                <l>Within me is the longest day&#8212;the sun wheels in slanting
                                    rings&#8212;it does not set for months</l>
                                <l>Stretched in due time within me the midnight sun just rises above
                                    the horizon and sinks again;</l>
                                <l>Within me zones, seas, cataracts, plants, volcanoes, groups,</l>
                                <l>Malaysia, Polynesia, and the great West Indian Islands.</l>
                            </lg>

                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>What do you hear, Walt Whitman?</l>
                            </lg>
                        </lg>


                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>But Walt Whitman sees and hears everything in the earth. The poem which he calls
                "Salut au Monde" is a long one. We have enough of it here to understand it, which
                readers at large both in America and here have not done, but have showered on the
                mediumistic poet all the epithets of "fool, madman, idiot," which the critic
                vocabulary can so plentifully furnish, with occasional praise equally extravagant.
                We have the key, and all is to us lucid as the sky and saner far than his deriders.
                How perfectly spiritual is this passage,&#8212;amongst the sights "of the deaths of
                the bodies of Gods"&#8212;Christ and others:&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <l>I see Hermes, unsuspected, dying, well-beloved, saying to the people,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Do not weep for me,</hi></l>
                            <l rend="italic">This is not my true country, I have lived banished from
                                my true country&#8212; I now go back there;</l>
                            <l rend="italic">I return to the celestial sphere, where every one goes
                                in his turn.</l>
                        </lg>

                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>In the "Song of the Broad Axe" we have the same unmistakable spirit
                vision:&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>I see the European headsman:</l>
                                <l>He stands masked, clothed in red, with huge legs and strong,
                                    naked arms,</l>
                                <l>And leans on a ponderous axe.</l>
                            </lg>

                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>Whom have you slaughtered lately, European headsman?</l>
                                <l>Whose is that blood upon you, so wet and sticky?</l>
                            </lg>

                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>I see the sunset of the Martyrs;</l>
                                <l>I see from the scaffolds of the descending ghosts,</l>
                                <l>Ghosts of dead lords, uncrowned ladies, impeached ministers,
                                    rejected kings,</l>
                            </lg>

                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>Rivals, traitors, poisoners, disgraced chieftains, and the
                                    rest.</l>
                                <l>I see those who in any land have died for the good cause;</l>
                                <l>The seed is spare, nevertheless the crop shall never run out.</l>
                                <l>(Mind you, O foreign kings, O priests, the crop shall never run
                                    out).</l>
                            </lg>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>But let us take a few passages as they occur <hi rend="italic">seriatim</hi> in the
                volume. Here is one which again proclaims his purpose:&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>I stand in my place, with my own day, here.</l>
                                <l>Here lands female and male;</l>
                                <l>Here the heirship and heiress-ship of the world&#8212;here the
                                    flame of materials;</l>
                                <l>Here Spirituality, the translatress, the open-avowed,</l>
                                <l>The ever-tending, the finale of visible forms;</l>
                                <l>The satisfier, after due, long waiting, now advancing,</l>
                                <l>Yes, here comes my mistress, the Soul.</l>
                            </lg>

                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>The Soul!</l>
                                <l>For ever and for ever&#8212;longer than soil is brown and
                                    solid&#8212;longer than water ebbs and flows.</l>
                                <l>I will make the poems of materials, for I think they are to be
                                    the most spiritual poems;</l>
                                <l>And I will make the poems of my body and of mortality,</l>
                                <l>For I think I shall then supply myself with the poems of my soul
                                    and immortality.</l>
                            </lg>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>To be truly spiritual is to be devout, and he adds&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">

                            <l>I say no man has ever been half devout enough,</l>
                            <l>None has ever yet adored or worshipped half enough;</l>
                            <l>None has begun to think how divine he himself is, and how certain the
                                future is.</l>

                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>But the spiritual poet must shew this:&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <l>The unseen and the seen;</l>
                            <l>Mysterious ocean where the streams empty;</l>
                            <l>Prophetic spirit of materials shifting and flickering around me;</l>
                            <l>Living beings, identities, now doubtless near us, in the air, that we
                                know not of;</l>
                            <l>Contact daily and hourly that will not release me.</l>
                        </lg>

                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>And he proceeds:&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <l>I will make the true poem of riches,&#8212;</l>
                            <l>To earn for the body and the mind whatever adheres, and goes forward
                                and is not dropped at death.</l>

                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>And again, of death and the soul:&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <l>Was somebody asking to see the Soul?</l>
                            <l>See! your own shape and countenance&#8212;persons, substances,
                                beasts, the trees, the running rivers, the rocks and sands.</l>
                            <l>All hold spiritual joys, and afterwards loosen them:</l>
                            <l>How can the real body ever die and be buried?</l>
                            <l>Of your real body, and any man's or woman's real body,</l>
                            <l>Item for item, it will elude the hands of the corpse-cleaners, and
                                pass to fitting spheres,</l>
                            <l>Carrying what has accrued to it from the moment of birth to the
                                moment of death.</l>

                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>In the most outward city pageant the open-eyed poet sees what the mere world-eyed
                mass never sees. In the reception of the Japanese Embassy at New York, he
                says:&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <l>I do not know whether others behold what I behold,</l>
                            <l>In the procession, along with the Princes of Asia, the
                                errand-bearers,</l>
                            <l>Bringing up the rear, hovering above, or in the ranks marching;</l>
                            <l>But I will sing you a song of what I behold</l>
                            <l>&#42; &#42; &#42; &#42; &#42; &#42; </l>
                            <l>Not the errand-bearing princes, nor the tanned Japanese only;</l>
                            <l>Lithe and silent the Hindoo appears&#8212;the Past, the Dead.</l>
                            <l>The murky night-morning of wonder and fable, inscrutable,</l>
                            <l>The enveloped mysteries, the old and unknown hive-bees,</l>
                            <l>The North&#8212;the sweltering South&#8212;Assyria&#8212;the
                                Hebrews&#8212;the Ancient of ancients,</l>
                            <l>Vast, desolated cities&#8212;the gliding Present&#8212;all of these,
                                and more are in the pageant procession.</l>

                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>Yes! to the poet of the opened eye&#8212;the spiritual poet and seer&#8212;all worlds
                and ages are open. The walls of Time, the barriers of the distant and of ages are
                thrown down; the manacles of the flesh are rent asunder; the mortal film has fallen
                from the eye of the temporal probationer, and, spirit-like, he walks cognizant amid
                the free things of the imperishable spheres. All times, people, regions, are present
                with him. He sees everything as it is, and knows better than ever that everything is
                miracle.</p>

            <p>Let us see what he says on this point:&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <head type="main-authorial">MIRACLES.</head>

                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <head type="main-authorial">1.</head>
                                <l>What shall I give? And what are my miracles?</l>
                            </lg>
                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <head type="main-authorial">2.</head>
                                <l>Realism is mine—my miracles—Take freely,</l>
                                <l>Take without end—I offer them to you wherever your feet can carry
                                    you, or your eyes reach.</l>
                            </lg>
                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <head type="main-authorial">3.</head>

                                <lg type="linegroup">
                                    <l>Why! who makes much of miracles?</l>
                                    <l>As for me I know of nothing else but miracles,</l>
                                    <l>Whether I walk the streets of Manhattan,<ref>&#42;</ref></l>
                                    <l>Or dart my sight over the roofs of houses toward the sky,</l>
                                    <l>Or wade with naked feet, along the beach, just in the edge of
                                        the water,</l>
                                    <l>Or stand under trees in the woods,</l>
                                    <l>Or talk with any one I love,</l>
                                    <l>Or sit at the table with my mother,</l>
                                    <l>Or look at strangers opposite me riding in the car,</l>
                                    <l>Or watch honey-bees busy round the hive, of a summer
                                        forenoon,</l>
                                    <l>Or animals feeding in the fields,</l>
                                    <l>Or birds&#8212;or the wonderfulness of insects in the
                                        air,</l>
                                    <l>Or the wonderfulness of the sun-down&#8212;or of stars
                                        shining, so quiet and bright,</l>
                                    <l>Or the exquisite, delicate, thin curve of the new moon in
                                        spring;</l>
                                    <l>Or whether I go among those I like best, and that like me
                                        best&#8212;mechanics, boatmen, farmers,</l>
                                    <l>Or among the <hi rend="italics">savans</hi>&#8212;or to the <hi 
                                        rend="italic">soir&#233;e</hi>&#8212;or to the opera,</l>
                                    <l>Or stand a long while looking at the movements of
                                        machinery,</l>
                                    <l>Or behold children at their sports,</l>
                                    <l>Or the admirable sight of the perfect old man, or the perfect
                                        old woman,</l>
                                    <l>Or the sick in the hospitals, or the dead carried to
                                        burial,</l>
                                    <l>Or my own eyes and figure in the glass;</l>
                                    <l>These, with the rest, one and all, are to me miracles,</l>
                                    <l>The whole referring&#8212;yet each distinct and in its
                                        place.</l>

                                </lg>

                                <lg type="linegroup">
                                    <head type="main-authorial">4.</head>
                                    <l>To me every hour of the light and dark is a miracle,</l>
                                    <l>Every inch of space is a miracle,</l>
                                    <l>Every square yard of the surface of the earth is spread with
                                        the same;</l>
                                    <l>Every cubit foot of the interior swarms with the same;</l>
                                    <l>Every spear of grass&#8212;the frames, limbs, organs of men
                                        and women, and all that concerns them,</l>
                                    <l>All these are to me unspeakably perfect miracles.</l>

                                </lg>

                                <lg type="linegroup">
                                    <l>To me the sea is a continual miracle;</l>
                                    <l>The fishes that swim&#8212;the rocks&#8212;the motion of the
                                        waves&#8212;the ships with men in them,</l>
                                    <l>What stranger miracles are there?</l>
                                </lg>
                            </lg>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>But enough: our object is not to bring forward all the spiritual matter of the
                volume&#8212;for it is all spiritual; we want only to shew our readers that another
                spiritual poet is amongst us, whom the world accepts because it thinks him merely
                eccentric and original. The poetry of Harris is very fine, but then he said out
                plumply that the spirits of departed poets gave it him, and the wise ones turned up
                their eyes and went on. Walt Whitman does not say that any spirit gave him these
                poems, but he shews it in every line to the initiated. It is alive with that fresh,
                new, piquant, magical life that no mere poet of the world, no Browning, or
                Swinburne, or Locker has. The moment that you dip into this poetry, you feel the
                stir and heavings of the limitless ocean of the God-world of deathless powers
                beneath; you are immersed in the eternal springs and streams of primal being. The
                harmonies and airs of the Summer Land are around you. You see and hear and feel and
                know with a new rush of faculties and consciousnesses which make even the most
                surprising of material discoveries flat and poor, for they penetrate only into the
                outer surface of outer things. Here you touch the fire-springs of creative life; you
                bathe in the life fountains; you are one with the countless hosts of the wise, the
                beautiful, the loving, who have emerged from the larva cells of earth into the
                perfected zones of eternal peace and poetry. What says your poet of his state
                there?</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <l>I lie abstracted, and hear beautiful tales of things and the reasons
                                of things:</l>
                            <l>They are so beautiful I nudge myself to listen.</l>

                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>His companions are yours: hear again!</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <l>Wild flowers and vines and weeds come up through the stones, and
                                hardly cover them.&#8212;Beyond these I pass,</l>
                            <l>Far, far in the forest, before I think where I go,</l>
                            <l>Solitary, smelling the earthly smell, stopping now and then in the
                                silence;</l>
                            <l>Alone I had thought&#8212;yet soon a silent troop gathers around
                                me;</l>
                            <l>Some walk by my side, and some behind, and some embrace my arms and
                                neck.</l>
                            <l>They, the spirits of friends dead or alive&#8212;thicker they come, a
                                great crowd, and I in the middle,</l>
                            <l>Collecting, dispensing, singing in spring, there I wander with
                                them.</l>
                            <l>&#42; &#42; &#42; &#42; &#42; &#42; &#42; </l>
                            <l>And twigs of maple, and a bunch of wild orange, and chestnut,</l>
                            <l>And stems of currants, and plum-blows, and the aromatic cedar.</l>
                            <l>These, I, compassed around by a thick cloud of spirits,</l>
                            <l>Wandering, point to, or touch as I pass, or throw them loosely from
                                me,</l>
                            <l>Indicating to each one what he shall have&#8212;giving something to
                                each.</l>

                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>With your poet you say finally&#8212;</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <l>Now, while the great thoughts of space and eternity fill me, I will
                                measure myself by them;</l>
                            <l>And now, touched with the lives of other globes, arrived as far along
                            as those of the earth,</l>
                            <l>Or waiting to arrive, or passed on farther than those of the earth,</l>
                            <l>Thenceforth I no more ignore them than I ignore my own life,</l>
                            <l>Or the lives of the earth arrived as far as mine, or waiting to
                                arrive.</l>
                            <l>O I see now that life can not exhibit all to me&#8212;as the day can
                                not,</l>
                            <l>I see that I am to wait for what will be exhibited by death.</l>

                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>Thus daily, whilst the earth porers of science pause and wonder, and then shrink from
                their own wondering, the broad day of the soul breaks more broadly; rushes on more
                peremptorily; spirits, issuing from their shy seclusion, speak out aloud, sing in
                troops and choruses to ears no longer astonished; come visibly and palpably; scatter
                over us flowers of heaven and of earth, make fire innocuous and touch disease into
                health; and poets, springing up here and there in the crowds, utter words of faith
                and vision ever and ever more startling and strong. It is high time that he that
                would have the credit of being wise should revise his wisdom, and let the mingling
                earth and heavens speak out to him of the new birth of things&#8212;new facts, new
                perceptions, new sights more wonderful than dreams, new sense of things, of justice,
                love, truth, pacification, and law&#8212;God in his world living through all in one
                perpetual and illimitable miracle.</p>

            <q who="Walt Whitman" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="poem">
                            <l>I swear I think there is nothing but immortality!</l>
                            <l>That the exquisite scheme is for it, and the nebulous float is for
                                it, and the cohering is for it!</l>
                            <l>And all preparation is for it! and identity is for it! and life and
                                death are altogether for it!</l>

                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>

            <p>And this invincible conviction is the backbone and substance of the new dispensation
                in which the poet tells us in his preface,"From the eyesight proceeds another eyesight, and 
                from the hearing proceeds another hearing, and from the voice proceeds another voice, 
                eternally curious of the harmony of things with man."</p>
            
            <p>True, Walt Whitman! True! Sing on, and let the whole world know it.</p>
            
            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">W. H.</signed> 
            </closer></div1>
            
            <div1 type="section"><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-left"/>
            
            <ab>&#42; New York.</ab></div1>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
